I greet you all in Jesus name happy new
year it is a privilege and a blessing
for us to be here this morning by God's
grace as I listen to the bereavements
being announced is you recognize that
actually it is by God's grace that you
are here this morning as we considered
we normally meet somewhere around August
to consider a plan for the following
year and we met in August last year to
consider what we should focus on in this
year and what our team should be and
taking into account the many things that
we saw happening in the nation we saw
happening in the church and in the lives
of various individuals we were led to
that theme taken from the words of one
old man calleb callebaut 85 years old
Joshua had conquered the land and it was
time for distribution of the land that
had been conquered and as he went about
giving land to various tribes various
individuals it came to the town of
calleb and Joshua was about to give him
a portion of the land that was conquered
but colep said no no no
while Moses was around he promised me
that it was giving going to give me a
piece of land you do sure we came with
you to this land to spite and I saw a
piece of land that I then asked Joshua
Moses and Moses granted me my request
therefore give me this mountain and that
is what we want to talk about that is
our theme for this year give me this
mountain this theme speaks about doing
the impossible in order to achieve that
which God has promised you next Sunday
we'll be going into details on what
calleb talked about but today we want to
look at the context within which those
words were spoken collab is 85 years old
I am getting there
amen he's only a few years and I'll be
there but he believed that even at 85 he
was still strong enough to conquer
Giants to conquer Giants and as I said
we'll look at that next week he was
ready to go against every odd to take up
new territory according to the promise
that God had given him and so this theme
is about keeping focus on the promises
of God not losing direction running here
and there pursuing things that don't
matter but it's about keeping focused on
the promises of God no matter how long
they take 45 years calibrated for his
territory and when it came he didn't say
now resort late what you live and do
with the land I'm 85 years old he said I
am as young today and enough strong
today as I was 45 years ago so we want
to in this year 2020 look back to the
promises of God
consider that circumstances that are
before us and be able to say like calleb
give me this mountain in fact even a
better way to say is give me my mountain
because that mountain had been promised
to him and he's saying give me my
mountain I don't want these other things
today as we consider the context of this
a particular statement I want us to talk
to look at the whole issue of focus and
vision because unless your vision a very
clear vision of focus you cannot conquer
your mountain especially when you are at
age 85 as most of us would know the
shaft ness or clarity of one's eyesight
is usually measured in what is called
visual acuity for example when we talk
about having a 20/20 vision which is
considered the correct or the perfect
vision eyesight 20/20 so when you say my
eyes are 20/20 you it means you have
good eyesight so when we talk about that
I'm told that what it means in real
terms is a very simple thing it means
that if you stand at 20 feet from an
object you see it in the same way that
any normal person with a good clear
vision would see it so it means you have
you can see an object at 20 feet in the
same way we're good a person with a good
eyesight can also see that object at 20
feet so you have a 20/20 vision if you
have a 2040 vision however some of us
have 20 40 some have twenty ten some of
twenty to thirty or 70 simply it means
that you will see at 20 feet
what are the ordinary people with good
vision see at 40 feet that's what means
2040 so you what when you stand at 20
feet you see what people see at 40 feet
so it means your vision is not in line
with the good vision the same with 2070
you see at 20 feet what people say at 70
feet so it means you have to move very
close to objects for you to see them
properly
one of the factors that naturally
impairs vision is old age with the
passage of time our eyesight tends to be
diminished we lose focus some of us
cannot see things that are near others
cannot see those things that are far I
glasses like the ones I'm wearing now
help us to refocus to put things in
their rightful place so that they can be
seen I still remember very clearly when
I discovered that I needed glasses
something that had resisted for a very
long time and some of you are still
resisting I was speaking to our youth in
out in Masai lodge they had an outing
there dinner and that invited me to come
to go and speak to them I had my Bible
my small Bible not on the phone or on
the tablet the lights were dim as they
do for dinners so when I stood to speak
and open my Bible
I could not read the text so I needed a
selfie stick you know to push this Bible
father and father away so that I could
be able to to read it my my selfie stick
my hand could not go far enough so I
would put it there and I could not read
anybody who does that so you keep
pushing things further and far away
until you run out of hand
to push it away you know that your
vision has been impaired it is no longer
good so I went to the what do you call
those people the doctor not optician
optician is the one that gives you
glasses opthamologist so he looked he
tested my eyesight and then finally
wrote for me a prescription which I went
with to an optician and I was given
glasses when I put them on suddenly my
Bible was so clear my vision was clear
was restored so I've been wearing this
glasses the interesting thing is that
this glasses are only for near things
those are my problem when I'm reading
things that are near that is when I need
glasses when I'm looking at you I
actually don't need them in fact when I
remove I see you more clearly
because my problem is with things that
are near so what they did this glasses
at the bottom there's a lens at the top
is clear glass so at the top I can see
you without having to use any lens my
vision was restored or sink or in sink
by those glasses
this was not a sickness this is part of
age are you together there's just that
time when your eyes now have served you
long enough and they say now we need
help so it is not a sickness there are
people who are cannot see properly
because they are sick their eyes are
sick mine were not sick when I went to
the doctor he didn't tell me I'm sick he
just said now you need glasses
and it was sorted out the truth is that
what happens to us in the natural also
tends to happen to our spiritual eyes as
time lapses our spiritual vision tends
also to disappear or to disintegrate to
diminish to get distorted as we stay
longer and longer in the Lord some
things we take for granted we do not see
the way we ought to see that is why as
the year begins like this a year has
closed and we are getting into a new
year vision is so important having the
right kind of vision so that you can see
things the way God sees them the way God
would want you to see them and so today
as we begin this theme of 20/20 give me
this mountain you cannot ask for a
mountain that you cannot see for you to
be able to ask for that mountain you
need to see and today I want to talk
about how do you maintain a clearer
20/20 vision so that you can see things
the way God sees them or the way God
would want you to see them so that you
can be able to get the things that God
has in store for you
Tech's today is found in Joshua chapter
12 verse number one to eight
and Joshua chapter thirteen also vast
number one to eight I realize our time
is fast friend so I'll not read the text
but we'll fix various sections as we go
along but I want to bring out two things
or three things that we must do in order
to refocus our vision in order to
restore our vision the way we were given
length I was given lenses that restored
my vision now I am able to read things
that are near I am able to see things
clearly because of the lenses that I was
given three lenses that I would like us
to receive or get in order to see things
clearly if we are going to capture our
mountain the first lens is a lens of
Thanksgiving the lens of Thanksgiving
appreciating past victories appreciating
fact past victories the second lens is a
lens of truth to self accepting current
realities and the third lens is the lens
of trust in God acknowledging future
possibilities in Joshua chapter 12 a
list is given of the many kings who were
defeated and whose territories were
taken by Israel both under Moses and
under Joshua in Joshua chapter 12 verse
1 and 2 the Bible says these are the
kings of the land whom the Israelite had
defeated and whose territory they took
over east of the Jordan from the iron
gorge to Mount Hermon including all the
eastern side of the Aruba seijo king of
the amorous who
trained in heshbon is listed for us in
verse number two in verse number four he
says and the territory of AAG king of
Bashan one of the last of the reversal
repla fights who reigned in asteroid and
a Dre in verse number seven and eight it
says these are the kings of the land
that joshua and israel has conquered on
the west side of the Jordan from Bar God
in the valley of lebanon to mount
Halleck which rises towards here their
Lance Joshua gave as an inheritance to
the tribes of Israel according to their
tribal divisions the hill country the
Western foothills the arab ax the
mountain slopes the desert and the Negev
the lands of the he ties amorous
Canaanites perizzites hivites and the
jebusites now this is the kind of text
which when you are reading for your
devotion you go quickly because there is
there can be no blessing here isn't it
this table says and gigas eyes and
ammonites and canonised and do Alec and
Hannah and all those things you just say
Lord let me move to something more
inspiring and I'm sure as I'm reading
this you are thinking where will we when
will we get to the real thing this is
the real thing what is the significance
of this list as time went by this list
was to serve as a corrective lens
through which Israel was to view every
situation that confronted them this list
is given here as a corrective lens like
the ones my doctor gave to me so that I
can be able to see things clearly this
list is a corrective lens because as
time goes by we have the tendency of
forgetting the things that God has done
and so this list
here was to remind them that the God who
had conquered these kings was still the
same God who was their God and this God
was able to do much more abundantly than
what he had done even in the previous
times two of these Kings were especially
crucial in Israel's history of conquest
one is found in verse number 2 and the
other is found in verse number 4 and if
you are a keen reader of the scriptures
you will find these two kings named over
and over again when Israel referred to
their conquest of Canaan the first one
was Sehun king of the emirates the other
one was
oak king of Bashan these two kings were
the superpowers of the time these two
kings were the Unconquered balls of the
time these two kings could not be
defeated when they came out to fight any
nation people trembled with fear
Sehun king of the Emirates and OGG king
of Bashan their defeat sent tremor into
the canaanites territory when it was
heard that xian had been defeated when
they heard that OGG had been defeated
Kenan was terrified of Israel when
Joshua sent out spies to Jericho a
rather heavy Joshua sent us since price
to Jericho Rahab confessed to this spies
that the since they had of his
the hearts of the people have done what
melted they have melted because of the
fame of Israel especially because they
had defeated Shihan king of the amorous
and OGG king of Bashan hundreds of years
later when the sublist wanted to remind
the children of Israel about the
greatness of God he wrote in some 136
that some that we often sing about he
wrote in verse number one of some 136
and he said Oh give thanks to the Lord
for he is good his mercies and doer
forever and he continues to list various
things that God has done and the service
goes ahead and lists many demonstrations
of the greatness of God and why he
should be praised and he punctuates each
line with his mercy and doers forever
out of this long list
the psalmist declares in verse number 17
of some 136 verse 17 to 22 is the
longest portion of that some dedicated
to any of the things that God had done
and to whom is that those verses
dedicated he says in verse number 17 to
him who struck down great kings for His
mercy endures forever and flew famous
kings for his mercy endures forever
Shihong king of the am arrives for his
mercy endures forever and AAG king of
Bashan for his mercy endures forever
and he gave their land as a heritage for
his mercy endures forever
a heritage to Israel his servant for his
mercy
Dewar's forever this was so significant
for Israel that God enabled them to
fight these two kings conquer them and
take their land and give to the children
of Israel Sammy says this was not our
doing this was the Lord's doing by His
mercies one of the things that readily
impairs our spiritual vision is
forgetfulness and you know forgetfulness
also comes with age as human beings we
have a high capacity to remember all the
bad things that have happened in our
lives and yet totally forget the good
things that we have experienced and so
as we come to a service like this and
you are looking of back over 20 19 over
20 18 over 20 16 over 2015 and you can
go as far back as possible
most likely the majority of us can
remember the bad things that happened to
us
is it true and so when my wife comes
here honest and honor they cassia and
calls people please come and give a
testimony of what the Lord has done
there is hardly anybody to come forward
for she got only three
but when we say now those of you who are
problems let me see how many of you this
morning have problems I know because
I've said you will not lift your hand
problems difficulties challenges all
these things have a way of robbing us of
the vision the perspective the reality
of what God has done you cannot conquer
a mountain that is ahead of you if you
cannot see how oak has been bitten if
you cannot see how she on has been
defeated hallelujah you can only go to
God and face the mountain that is before
you when you have the clarity of what
God is able to do because you have seen
him in your life past you have seen him
defeat here on king of the amorites you
have seen him defeat oak king of Bashan
if I was one of those preachers out of
saying tell your neighbor she horn
tell your neighbor oak Siwon has been
defeated his masses endure forever
aaaghh has been defeated his masses and
you are forever is there anybody in the
house this morning is there anybody who
can testify that she won in your life
has been defeated
anybody who can look back and you had a
superpower in your life the great thing
that difficult thing that you thought
would finish you completely God by His
grace came through for you and defeated
Shihan king of the ammonites defeated
AAG king of Bashan and now you can say
Oh
give thanks to the Lord for His mercy
and you are forever hallelujah
we must put on the lens of Thanksgiving
otherwise we will not see our Mountain
unless you can see the invisible you
cannot conquer the visible God wants to
give us a clear vision a 20/20 vision of
who he is we must therefore pose and
appreciate the small and great things
God has done in our lives
20:19 was difficult many people have
testified but it is in that same 20:19
that God dealt with Org in your life
maybe you were sick and God healed you
you did not have a job but God gave you
one the floods came but they did not
come near your house there were
accidents but you are here God has done
something great his mercies and your
forever put on the lens of Thanksgiving
I just look back over your life and say
surely God you have been good to me go
back and read that some 136 I see the
list of the thing that the sum is list
down the things that God did the things
that God did they think that God did and
he sometimes he breaks a sentence into
two and says and he did this and His
mercy and us forever so that this
disease and His mercy endures forever
because he doesn't want to complete that
fellowship with God and a precision of
God too quickly too soon the second lens
is the lens of truth to self truth to
self accepting current realities
accepting current realities in chapter
13 verse number 1 to 8 the Bible says
when Joshua was old and well advanced in
years the Lord said to him you are very
old and they are still very large areas
of land to be taken over this is the
land that remains all the regions of the
Philistines and goro sites from the
siwon river on the east of Egypt to the
territory of Akron on the north and all
of it counted as canonized territory the
territory of the five Philistine rulers
in Gaza Ashdod Ashkelon God and Akron
that of the average of its from the
south all the land of the canaanites
from era of the sidonians
as far as affect the region of the
amorous the sea of the gibbets and all
the area of the gabba it's an all
lebanon to the east from Valgard below
Mount Hermon to labor hamath another not
very inspiring text of Scripture
but the Bible says all Scripture is
inspired by God and it is profitable for
all these things that he tells Timothy
so this is text is inspired by God what
is God saying here what is this tech
telling us that there are certain
realities as we face our mountains as we
face our future as we face the testing
that God has called us
every person has certain realities that
we have to just accept this our
realities it is the lens of truth to
self being true to yourself let's see
what reality is brought here the first
reality we see here is about age and I
know age is a very sensitive subject but
listen to what God tells Joshua you are
very old did you see that you are very
old when the Ancient of Days tells you
you are old you must be old one was
lived from everlasting to everlasting
tells you you are very old you must be
very old even if you want to hide so
cartel's Joshua you are very old and so
Joshua though he had done a great job in
leading the major campaigns and
conquering kingdoms age had caught up
with him and age will catch up with you
age will catch up with me
perhaps it has already caught up with me
and so God is aware that you are old
God is away how old you are
he tells you my friend David you are
very old you are very old and I say Amen
life is good at sixty amen
so the second reality that comes out in
this text of Scripture
is that not all the land that he had
given to Joshua had been conquered the
Lord says to Joshua you are very old and
there are still very large areas of land
to be taken over in other words the work
is not yet complete you have done very
well but work still remains God then cos
I had to describe the land that is still
left and from the description of the
land if you have a Bible map you will
find that actually the land they had
conquered was much smaller than the land
that was not yet conquered so there was
still a much bigger land to be conquered
some of the realities that confront many
of us as we come to the start of a new
year is that we are growing older and we
have not accomplished much this
sometimes puts people into a state of
crisis especially those of us who are
entering into the medias have you ever
heard of something called the midlife
crisis midlife crisis is a crisis that
happens to a person in the middle years
40 and above
where they suddenly realize that where I
am going is nearer than where I have
come from that is not the real cause of
the crisis the real cause of the crisis
comes what I have accomplished with all
the years that have been given is less
than what still lies ahead of me and so
people begin to look at their lives and
say what have I accomplished with my
life I have no 50 years old what have I
achieved and people get into a state of
crisis many people get paralyzed in that
state of crisis many people make serious
mistakes in that state of crisis this is
where men particularly men do crazy
things because they are realizing that
they are getting very old now in order
to satisfy themselves and assure
themselves that I am NOT as old as I
look
they go out for a young girl to convince
them to accept them and when this young
girl accepts them they say I can't be
that bad if this beautiful girl can
accept me I am okay that's why you find
in the ages of 40 and above people tend
to marry second wives those who can't
marry those who cannot marry tend to
keep concubines in another estate
somewhere those who cannot keep
concubines have this one stint here and
there and everywhere what are they
trying to show that I'm still strong as
I was last year
that's not what your shirt colored meant
and so they get into a state of crisis
ladies in those edges begin to act like
girls you find a good old lady of 45 who
is very old or let's push it to 60 you
find a good old lady of 60 wearing a
skirt that is up to here and like one of
my pastors said now you're wearing a
truss a skirt or dress that is hanging
up to here
what you don't realize that when you
were younger you had something to show
but now they have with odds
[Applause]
so what are you trying to show with a
dress that is up to here why don't you
cover the thing as far as you can it is
called crisis it's a midlife crisis
so you find this all nice lady with a
very tight trouser my goodness in those
days you had something to show but now
those things are over my friend
just accept the realities of life God is
saying now you are very old I'll be
together
yeah and they sell more lot to be
conquered just except for me I've
accepted I have told you people I turned
60 with situm and I am very happy
because that is the real reality amen I
cannot run away from it I cannot change
it it is the reality
God says organdy you are old and I say
MA
we have grown old together with our
Ancient of Days so Joshua is told my
friend you're growing older in the
pursuit of your dreams some of us get
very shocked you are suddenly confronted
by the realization that time is running
out or has already run out on you you
look back over your life and though you
have made some progress your original
dream is not yet realized and yet time
is gone
there is still much land to be conquered
these two realities can be paralyzing
but let me tell you if you put on their
correct lenses you'll be okay
hallelujah you will be okay you will see
things clearly you will see things in
perspective you'll see things okay
you will not panic how do you maintain a
20/20 vision in such circumstances by
recognizing that God knows the realities
of your life God knows the realities of
your life God knew that Joshua was old
in fact very old God knew that much land
had not yet been conquered in fact he
knew the exact territory and described
it - you're sure I want to tell you
brothers and sisters God knows that yet
another year has ended but you do not
yet have a job God knows that you have
been sick for five months or five years
or five weeks God knows God knows that
you have been in a troubled marriage for
seven years he knows God knows that you
are running on turning 40 and you are
still single God knows that you are
single in fact I can tell you are very
single so it is not something that God
is unaware about just put on the right
lenses and say God knows tell your
neighbor now God knows
so when when people come and tell you
hey my society time is running out of
news a God knows
hallelujah Karnas you have been sick for
so long God knows he knows why he has
allowed you to stay in that state for
this long he knows now he not only knows
but he has a plan I'll finish with that
so the fact that another year is ended
is a non-issue to God
in fact he himself can come to tell you
you're old you're sick you're jobless
you are this you are that you are the
other
he knows therefore instead of fighting
with the life instead of losing your
sleep over unconquered territory
instead of backsliding because you are
still single and go and marry an
unbeliever my advice to you is wait on
God wait on God lift up your eyes to
heaven look to Jesus the author and the
finisher of your faith he knows
consider this Israel had been in slavery
for 400 years 400 years slavery
their oppressors had bitten their back
to pulp
when Moses tried to help them they drove
him out of town in their frustration
that God was aware God knew that they
were in slavery and so one day he came
to Moses and told him in Exodus chapter
3 verse 7 the Lord said to Moses I have
indeed seen the misery of my people in
Egypt I have heard them crying out
because of their slave drivers I am
concerned about their suffering so I
have come down to rescue them from the
hand of the Egyptian and to bring them
out of the land into good and spacious
land
a land flowing with milk and honey it is
God Himself who left heaven and came to
Moses and say I know my children are
suffering in Egypt I have come to
deliver them
God knows where you are if you are going
to enjoy 20/20 your vision must change
put on the lenses of truth to self look
at yourself and say I am fearfully and
wonderfully made I am in the right place
it may be difficult but God is with me I
realized my time is up long up but God
knows
[Laughter]
let me put on the last lens the lens of
trust acknowledging future possibilities
this is the best part your vision 2020
must be based and clarified and put in
sync with the lens of trust trust in God
sometimes when we are faced with agent
on conquered land we can panic and have
said that but we must acknowledge that
God knows only knows but he also has a
plan when God spoke about Joshua's age
and the remaining territory it was not
with any sense of panic not at all
what was God's perspective of the
Unconquered land listen to this in verse
number 6 of chapter 13 the Bible says
asked for all the inhabitants of the
mountain regions from Lebanon to miss
referred name that is all the sidonians
listen to this I myself will drive them
out before the Israelites hallelujah who
is I myself God
be sure to allocate this land to Israel
for an inheritance as I have instructed
you oh my goodness I don't know whether
you are seeing what I'm seeing
these are the kind of texts of passages
that make me very excited because what
God is saying is that land is not yet
conquered and God knows how much land is
not yet conquered and it tells Joshua
you you are old me I am NOT I'm still in
business
hallelujah so I myself I am going to
conquer this land your task now is to do
what I located to the children of Israel
God is saying allocate land which is not
yet conquered that is a step of faith in
other words you take a step of faith and
do things as if they have already
happened that's what faith is all about
hallelujah
so he says divide this land to the
people I located this is a powerful
promise God promised Joshua that he
himself is going to take care of the
situation I myself will drive it out
drive them out what was the implication
of this in light of Joshua's current
reality the implication is that though
Joshua was old and advanced in years his
God was not old and advanced in years
his God was still alive and able to do
far more abundantly than what he asked
or imagined
God does not age he does not grow weary
he does not change he's the same
yesterday today and forever therefore
though there was some conquered land the
Ancient of Days was going to conquer it
himself in his time do you know when
that land was conquered the whole of it
hundreds of years later in the day of
King David in the days of King David
David conquered that land and the Bible
says and God gave him rest from all his
enemies
you may be worried about your children
I'm growing old
I have no inheritance to live for my
children give them the little that you
have God knows God will take care of
them God will take care of them it does
not matter so brothers and sisters as we
get into this year as we get into this
time there is not panic stop struggling
with issues stopped struggling with
people focus on God put on new lenses
begin to see things the way God sees
them and you will be perfectly okay
pastor come and close for us hallelujah
[Applause]
[Music]